<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bricabrac</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/</id><updated>2017-03-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>a personal thought on anarchism</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/a-personal-thought-on-anarchism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>bricabrac</name></author><id>tag:bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu,2017-03-13:/en/a-personal-thought-on-anarchism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anarchy is not about disorder nor insecurity. Anarchism does not advocate a state—in the original sense of the word—of anomy. But it is the State which perpetuates violence and disorder. Anarchy means the absence of both the State and the laws. Élisée Reclus would see it as the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anarchy is not about disorder nor insecurity. Anarchism does not advocate a state—in the original sense of the word—of anomy. But it is the State which perpetuates violence and disorder. Anarchy means the absence of both the State and the laws. Élisée Reclus would see it as the “higher expression of order.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anarchism is not an anti-social nor individualist thought. On the contrary, anarchism represents the wish of a fair and free society, which can be reached only through the real freedom of the individuals whom society consists of. A fair and free society cannot be based on coercion. However, real freedom does not mean the power of doing what one wants at the expense of the others' freedom. Real and fair freedom is also for one to  willfully set restraints to its freedom, without them being commanded by any authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, anarchism is caricatured by those who cannot conceive of an organised and fair society without institutions such as private property, the State or the police, that most of anarchists reject. The republican ideology, statist and nationalist, prevails in the political discourse, wether on left-wing or right-wing, and it does not cease to be taught by its institutions, the first of them we face being the so-called “republican” school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anarchy is not equal to a society based on the survival of the fittest, as we may be often told being an anarchist or related to. This principle that “might is right”, we currently know it, strengthened by the capitalist mode of production and its neo-liberal version. Survival of the fittest will cease when we understand that competition and rivalry between individuals must give way to free cooperation. The end of its existence will be sealed by the withdrawal of the society based on classes, supposed races or privileged models of sexuality and gender. In short, when domination of some over others is nothing more than a bad memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anarchism is not utopist nor extremist, but it is radical, which means it considers the resolution of issues at their roots. We do not stop the boiling water from making the pot overflow differently than by turning the fire off. Thus, we cannot settle for wanting to solve issues which roots are deeply buried in our society's structures by amending or hacking them, but by destroying them to rebuild some better. We cannot reach social justice through laws or authoritarian institutions, for it would jeopardise our freedom as individuals. Thus, it is futile to blindly trust reformist projects such as rewriting the constitution and reforming the Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot settle for legal actions in order to reach our aspirations, that is, social justice and freedom. Overtaking the State must be done through realizing that its existence is not inavoidable nor essential, and that all of what results from it is no panacea. Overtaking the State also means overtaking its rules if they are in conflict with social justice and freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot give in to anti-intellectualism nor to contempt for class. Knowledge must be open to everyone without being commanded to them. The only essential knowledge is that of skepticism and questioning, particularly regarding what seems obvious and acknowledged. For that knowledge allows us to analyse the ideological discourse without being leveraged by something other than our sole belief, and to know, to spot and finally to overtake the bias imposed to our thought by our position within the social hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must decline every form of eugenics, in particular intellectual eugenics. Ambition can also work in the “refusal to make it” way, which can be a sign of wisdom and solidarity more than social failure or stupidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must not think that our opinion, our thought, can embrace an ideology in its entirety. What matters is not to be exemplary nor to be the goog learner of some “&lt;em&gt;dire-vrai&lt;/em&gt;” (tell-true), but to ensure consistency with our belief. Socrates would tell us that think is such as talk to oneself, and that what matters is not to agree with everyone around the world but rather to agree with oneself. Thus, anarchism, if it is based on some common principles, has nothing to do with a settled ideology. On the contrary, it is designed to be figured continuously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thought does not tackle neither all of the topics which can be analyzed with an anarchist point of view nor all of the forms that anarchism can take. This may constitute another post on this web-log.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>about the nouveau parti anticapitaliste</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/npa.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>bricabrac</name></author><id>tag:bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu,2017-02-26:/en/npa.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I watched &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p32rXHenjHo"&gt;an interview of Philippe Poutou by a journalist of the on-line newspaper Mediapart&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://npa2009.org/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nouveau Parti Anti-capitaliste&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;'s 2017 runner for President of the French republic, and I must say that I have been rather pleasantly surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider myself as a libertarian anarchist. I do not …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I watched &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p32rXHenjHo"&gt;an interview of Philippe Poutou by a journalist of the on-line newspaper Mediapart&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://npa2009.org/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nouveau Parti Anti-capitaliste&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;'s 2017 runner for President of the French republic, and I must say that I have been rather pleasantly surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider myself as a libertarian anarchist. I do not believe in both the State and elections. Although they relayed a trotskyst thought, the words of the NPA's candidate highlighted the fact that both his party and his application for the Presidential election have wanted to exist during this electoral campaign with the aim of gathering the anticapitalism's activists and sympathizers, from libertarian anarchists to trotskysts, including zadists and revolutionary union activists. Poutou also talked about democracy, self-governance, internationalism, anti-racism, anti-sexism and anti-homophobia, environmental struggle, breaking with capitalism and the regaining of the political power by the exploited. In the end, what he said suggested a wish of emancipation from the State which we originally find in the Marxian political philosophy, by opposing the riot from the election – a paradox that the NPA's members accept deliberately. In short, many common points for a few divergences regarding my own political opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also emphasized the necessity of radicality incumbent upon us by criticizing in particular the protectionism which is very popular with the so-called “radical left” represented by &lt;em&gt;la France Insoumise&lt;/em&gt; and, a fortiori, Mélenchon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also talked about the issue of the far-leftist movements' scattering, within trade unions and diverse action groups, and about how they are used to praise their house, a final point which is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will not vote for the NPA for I do not understand its wish to run for the National election. However, I would consider NPA's applications for local elections as positive moves in a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian_municipalism"&gt;libertarian municipalist&lt;/a&gt; perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>sur le nouveau parti anticapitaliste</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/../npa.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>bricabrac</name></author><id>tag:bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu,2017-02-26:/en/../npa.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Je regardais aujourd'hui &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p32rXHenjHo"&gt;une interview par un journaliste de Mediapart de Philippe Poutou&lt;/a&gt;, candidat du &lt;a href="https://npa2009.org/"&gt;Nouveau Parti Anti-capitaliste&lt;/a&gt; à l'élection présidentielle de 2017, et j'ai été agréablement surpris par son discours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je me considère comme libertaire. Je ne crois ni à l'État ni aux élections. Bien que transmettant une pensée …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Je regardais aujourd'hui &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p32rXHenjHo"&gt;une interview par un journaliste de Mediapart de Philippe Poutou&lt;/a&gt;, candidat du &lt;a href="https://npa2009.org/"&gt;Nouveau Parti Anti-capitaliste&lt;/a&gt; à l'élection présidentielle de 2017, et j'ai été agréablement surpris par son discours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je me considère comme libertaire. Je ne crois ni à l'État ni aux élections. Bien que transmettant une pensée trotskyste, les dires du candidat du NPA mettent ici l'accent sur le fait que son parti et sa candidature à l'élection souhaitent exister lors de cette campagne électorale dans le but de rassembler la sphère militante et sympathisante de l'anti-capitalisme, des libertaires aux trotskystes, en passant par les zadistes et les syndicalistes. Poutou parle également de démocratie, d'auto-gestion, d'internationalisme et d'anti-racisme, d'anti-sexisme et d'anti-homophobie, de lutte écologique, de rupture avec le capitalisme et de ré-appropriation du pouvoir politique par les exploité·e·s. Il laisse au final esquisser un désir d'émancipation de l'État que l'on retrouve à l'origine dans la philosphie politique de Karl Marx, en opposant la révolte et le combat face à l'élection – paradoxe que les membres du NPA souhaitent assumer. Bref, beaucoup de points communs pour quelques divergences avec mes opinions politiques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il appuyes aussi sur la nécessité de radicalité qui nous incombe aujourd'hui, en critiquant notamment le protectionisme plébiscité par la gauche « radicale » de la France Insoumise et a fortiori de Mélenchon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il parle également du problème de l'éparpillement des mouvances d'extrême-gauche, au sein des syndicats et des divers groupes de lutte, de leurs « &lt;em&gt;habitudes boutiquières&lt;/em&gt; », ce dernier point étant intéressant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je ne voterai pas pour autant pour le NPA, car je ne comprends pas sa volonté de se présenter à des élections nationales. Je verrai en revanche d'un bon oeil des candidatures de ce parti au niveau local, dans une optique de rapprochement avec le &lt;a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Municipalisme_libertaire"&gt;municipalisme libertaire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>how to git</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/how-to-git.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>bricabrac</name></author><id>tag:bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu,2017-02-23:/en/how-to-git.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For a few days, I have signed up for a &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; in order to contribute to the translation of diverse free-software projects. Even though I have already known its main idea, the proper using of the git version control system has always seemed to me as a complex and far-fetched …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For a few days, I have signed up for a &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; in order to contribute to the translation of diverse free-software projects. Even though I have already known its main idea, the proper using of the git version control system has always seemed to me as a complex and far-fetched process. However, I have seriously dug into it these least few days and have been gradually getting used to the various commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will draw here a brief reminder of the workflow that I have learnt and that I currently use when I contribute to a project which I am not the owner; that is, nearly all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Forking et cloning the remote repository&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After forking the original project repository on Github, we need to clone the fork repo locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;cd path/of/your/working/dir
git clone &amp;lt;fork-url&amp;gt;
cd &amp;lt;fork-dir&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then we add a remote that will be named &lt;code&gt;upstream&lt;/code&gt; with the upstream repo's url.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git remote add upstream &amp;lt;upstream-repo-url&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we check the remots with &lt;code&gt;git remote -v&lt;/code&gt;, the terminal should return these lines :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;origin  https://fork.git (fetch)
origin  https://fork.git (push)
upstream    https://upstream-repo.git (fetch)
upstream    https://upstream-repo.git (push)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Making changes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps which follow the changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We update locally from the upstream repo and we create a new branch for the commit-to-be :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git fetch upstream
git branch &amp;lt;new-branch&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We add the modified files to push to the commit queue :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git add &amp;lt;modified-file&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Commit :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git commit -m &amp;quot;Commit message&amp;quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We push the commit to the fork repo we own :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git push origin &amp;lt;new-branch&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We complete the operation by going back on Github to issue a pull request from the fork to the upstream repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Syncing a fork&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that stage, let us say the pull has been merged into the upstream repository by its owner. We now sync the fork with the upstream repo in order to be up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We fetch the updates from upstream :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git fetch upstream
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We go back to the master branch :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git checkout master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We merge the upstream/master branch with the local master branch :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git merge upstream/master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And we push all the stuff to the remote fork :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git push origin master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last edit on 23 february 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>how to git</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/../how-to-git.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>bricabrac</name></author><id>tag:bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu,2017-02-23:/en/../how-to-git.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Depuis peu de temps, je me suis inscrit sur &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; afin de contribuer à la traduction de divers projets de logiciels libres. Bien que je connaissais déjà le principe, l'utilisation propre du logiciel de gestion de versions git m'a toujours semblé complexe et tiré par les cheveux. Mais ces derniers …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Depuis peu de temps, je me suis inscrit sur &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; afin de contribuer à la traduction de divers projets de logiciels libres. Bien que je connaissais déjà le principe, l'utilisation propre du logiciel de gestion de versions git m'a toujours semblé complexe et tiré par les cheveux. Mais ces derniers jours, je m'y suis mis sérieusement et j'apprends petit à petit à me familiariser avec les diverses commandes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je présenterai ici un pense-bête du workflow que j'utilise quand je contribue à des projets dont je ne suis pas l'initiateur; quasiment tous, donc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Fork et clonage du dépôt distant&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Après avoir forké le dépôt original du projet concerné sur la plateforme Github, il faut cloner le dépôt du fork en local.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;cd chemin/de/votre/dossier/de/travail
git clone &amp;lt;adresse-du-fork&amp;gt;
cd &amp;lt;dossier-du-fork&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On ajoute un dépôt distant qu'on nommera &lt;code&gt;upstream&lt;/code&gt; avec l'adresse du dépôt upstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git remote add upstream &amp;lt;adresse-du-dépôt-upstream&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Si on vérifie la configuration des dépôt distants avec la commande &lt;code&gt;git remote -v&lt;/code&gt;, on devrait avoir ça :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;origin  https://fork.git (fetch)
origin  https://fork.git (push)
upstream    https://projet-original.git (fetch)
upstream    https://projet-original.git (push)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Faire des modifications&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voici les étapes que suivront les modifications faites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On met à jour depuis le dépôt upstream et on crée une nouvelle branche pour le futur commit :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git fetch upstream
git branch &amp;lt;nouvelle-branche&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On ajoute les fichiers à pousser dans la liste d'attente :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git add &amp;lt;fichier-modifié&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On commit :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git commit -m &amp;quot;Message du commit&amp;quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On pousse le commit sur le dépôt du fork, qui nous appartient :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git push origin &amp;lt;nouvelle-branche&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On termine en retournant sur Github pour faire une pull request depuis le fork vers le dépôt upstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Synchronisation du fork&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imaginons qu'à ce stade, la pull request a été fusionnée dans le dépôt upstream par son propriétaire. On va maintenant synchroniser le fork avec le dépôt upstream pour être jour dans les commits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On récupère les mise à jour depuis upstream :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git fetch upstream
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On retourne dans la branche master :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git checkout master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On fusionne la branche upstream/master avec la branche master locale :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git merge upstream/master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On pousse tout ça sur le fork distant :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git push origin master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dernière modification le 23 février 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>perspectives</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/perspectives.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>bricabrac</name></author><id>tag:bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu,2016-12-14:/en/perspectives.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I do not like to work. At least, I do not like to work when constrained by a hierarchy ; under pressure from the competitive relationship between companies, the sacrosanct principle of economic liberalism and capitalist mode of production ; burdened by the weight of an unpleasant and unfulfilling job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I do not like to work. At least, I do not like to work when constrained by a hierarchy ; under pressure from the competitive relationship between companies, the sacrosanct principle of economic liberalism and capitalist mode of production ; burdened by the weight of an unpleasant and unfulfilling job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make these consideratons while we are still a student without any working experience but a few internship and roughly two or three seasonal contracts is likely to make you feel down. Not yet fully entered in the labour market as an employee but already blasé.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually no. I am talking about being an employee, but when you are a student with all the doors that are still open to you—thanks to your educational level—people are trying to lure you with other shapes of alienation at work: self-entrepreneurship, academic research or teaching, even 'ethical' wage-earning within young, trendy, dynamic, bio-friendly, leftist-but-not-too-far-because-extremes-are-evil companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is what I want to talk about: this situation where, because of your academic educational background and a fortiori your cultural capital, you are to enter, unwillingly, the hybrid class which some would call the medium class: aware of the upper class privilege, but not aware of theirs ; aware of environmental, political and social issues, but without appreciate their incidence on the said issues. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the questions I am hardly able to answer to being a student and considering my beliefs: can I follow the pattern which I have been pre-determined to follow since I reached college—research and teaching—while maintaining a class consciousness? Aren't I to forget unavoidably that the acamedic status would have provided me new privilege to enjoy? Will I still have an enough critical thinking to take into account my social position in my vision in order not to be biased by a social confinement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My fear is precisely that of believing that my educational level would allow me to work and still have a fulfilling life, because I would have the opportunity to do something that pleases me. For it is exactly the feeling that I get from the medium class, to which I already belong more or less: that of a class which is not aware of its position within the social hierarchy. This blindness is doubtless one of the reasons why any revolutionary process remains impossible today: how can it be possible to envisage another society whitout being conscious of the alienations from which we suffer and that we inflict to the others? Above all, how can it be possible to realize the urgent need of a societal shift?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense, my interrogations about my immediate future illustrate the class struggle on my scale: even though I can find a strictly intellectual interest in pursuing my education up to the PhD and take pleasure in it, pride is also likely to make me seek a higher social status. I always refer this very consideration to an article published on an issue of CQFD, titled &lt;a href="http://cqfd-journal.org/Refus-de-parvenir"&gt;"Le refus de parvenir"&lt;/a&gt; (Iffik Le Guen, avril 2016), discussing the conscious refusal of seeking a higher social status within a system, quite often through work: kinf of an inverted ambition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I follow my interest in intellectual knowledge while hoping to keep my critical eye and my class consciousness, and use this knowledge in concrete forms of resistance, or should I turn now to more basic projects and closer to the struggle in a perspective of refusal to contribute to a system which revulses me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS : Here is an answer written by Adonis Loisot on his &lt;em&gt;Capharnaüm cacographique&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href="https://caca.grainedutopie.eu/perspectives.html"&gt;Perspectives d'un universitaire aliéné&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>perspectives</title><link href="https://bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu/en/../perspectives.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>bricabrac</name></author><id>tag:bricabrac.grainedutopie.eu,2016-12-14:/en/../perspectives.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Je n’aime pas travailler. Du moins, je n’aime pas travailler sous la contrainte d’une hiérarchie ; sous la pression qu’implique la relation concurrentielle entre les entreprises, sacro-saint principe du libéralisme économique et du mode de production capitaliste ; sous le poids d’un travail désagréable ou non épanouissant …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Je n’aime pas travailler. Du moins, je n’aime pas travailler sous la contrainte d’une hiérarchie ; sous la pression qu’implique la relation concurrentielle entre les entreprises, sacro-saint principe du libéralisme économique et du mode de production capitaliste ; sous le poids d’un travail désagréable ou non épanouissant, simplement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faire ces considérations quand on est encore étudiant et que ses expériences au boulot peuvent se compter sur les doigts d'une main, ça a de quoi faire broyer du noir. Pas encore totalement rentré dans le rang du salariat, et déjà blasé.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En fait non. Je parle de salariat, mais lorsque l’on est étudiant et que pas mal de portes nous restent encore ouvertes grâce à notre niveau d’instruction, on nous fait aussi miroiter d’autres modes d’aliénation au travail : l’auto-entrepreneuriat, la recherche et l’enseignement universitaires, voire le salariat « éthique » dans des boîtes jeunes, branchées, dynamiques, où ça mange bio, où ça vote à gauche mais pas trop parce que les extrêmes c’est le mal, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Et c’est bien de ça que je veux parler : cette situation où, de par son niveau d’instruction universitaire et a fortiori de son capital culturel, on s’apprête à rentrer, malgré soi et en tant qu'adulte, dans la classe bâtarde que certain·e·s appelleront la classe moyenne : consciente des privilèges des classes supérieures, mais pas des siens ; consciente des problèmes environnementaux, politiques et sociaux, mais sans se rendre compte de sa participation aux dits problèmes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voilà les questions auxquelles j’ai tant de mal à répondre en tant qu’étudiant et considérant mes convictions : puis-je suivre la voie qui m’est pré-établie depuis mon entrée à l’université, c’est-à-dire le domaine de la recherche et de l’enseignement, tout en gardant une conscience de classe ? Ne vais-je pas, inévitablement, oublier le fait que le statut d’universitaire m’aura apporté de nouveaux privilèges desquels jouir ? Aurai-je encore assez d’esprit critique pour prendre en compte cette position sociale dans ma vision afin de ne pas la voire biaisée par un enfermement dans une certaine bulle sociale ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mon inquiétude est précisément celle de croire au fait que mon niveau d’instruction me permette de travailler sans être aliéné, car j’aurai l’occasion de faire quelque chose qui me plaît. Car c’est exactement le sentiment que me renvoie la classe moyenne, dont je fais déjà partie en quelque sorte : celui d’une classe inconsciente de sa position dans la hiérarchie sociale. Cet aveuglement est sans doute une des causes rendant impossible tout processus révolutionnaire aujourd’hui : sans la conscience des aliénations subies et de celles que l’on fait subir aux autres, comment est-il possible d’imaginer une autre société ? Et surtout, comment est-il possible de se rendre compte du besoin urgent d’un changement de société ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ainsi, mes interrogations sur mon avenir proche illustrent en quelque sorte la lutte des classes à mon échelle : si je peux avoir un intérêt purement intellectuel et avoir du plaisir à poursuivre mes études jusqu’à un doctorat, il y a sûrement une part d’orgueil qui me pousse à vouloir le faire dans le but de m’élever socialement. Cette considération me renvoie à un article paru dans un numéro de CQFD, intitulé &lt;a href="http://cqfd-journal.org/Refus-de-parvenir"&gt;"Le refus de parvenir"&lt;/a&gt; (Iffik Le Guen, avril 2016), traitant du refus conscient de s’élever socialement au sein d’un système, bien souvent par le biais du travail : une sorte d’ambition inversée.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dois-je suivre mon intérêt pour la connaissance intellectuelle en espérant conserver mon esprit critique et ma conscience de classe, et mettre cette connaissance à profit dans des formes concrètes de résistance, ou dois-je me tourner dès maintenant vers des projets plus basiques et plus proches de la lutte dans une optique de refus de contribuer au système qui me dégoûte ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS : Adonis Loisot a rédigé un commentaire de cet article sur son Capharnaüm cacographique, si ça vous intéresse, vous pouvez le trouver ici : &lt;a href="https://caca.grainedutopie.eu/perspectives.html"&gt;Perspectives d'un universitaire aliéné&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>